<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the Barmudas, otherwise called the Ile of Diuels by Sir Thomas Gates, Sir George Sommers, and Captayne Newport, with diuers others. Set forth for the loue of my country, and also for the good of the plantation in Virginia. Sil. Iourdan.</title>
            <author>Jourdain, Silvester, d. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109240</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844890</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 720:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the Barmudas, otherwise called the Ile of Diuels by Sir Thomas Gates, Sir George Sommers, and Captayne Newport, with diuers others. Set forth for the loue of my country, and also for the good of the plantation in Virginia. Sil. Iourdan.</title>
                  <author>Jourdain, Silvester, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Windet, and are to be sold by Roger Barnes in S. Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleet-streete, vnder the Diall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bermuda Islands --  Discovery and exploration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THE BARMV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAS, OTHERWISE called the Ile of DIVELS: By Sir THOMAS GATES, Sir GEORGE SOMMERS, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne NEWPORT, with diuers others. Set forth for the loue of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and alſo for the good of the Plantation in Virginia.</p>
            <p>SIL. IOVRDAN.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Windet,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Roger Barnes</hi> in <hi>S. Dunſtanes</hi> Church-yard in Fleet-ſtreete, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Diall. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Maſter IOHN FITZ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IAMES Eſquire, one of his MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties chiefe Iuſtices of Peace within the Countie of DORSET.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, Amongſt all the ſinnes, that humane nature doth ſtand poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with, ingratitude, doth challenge a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie in man, although it bee a thing repugnant to reaſon, and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with all mutuall focietie. To free myſelfe from this <hi>vitium naturae,</hi> I am bold in theſe fewe lines to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate my loue to you: for it were
<pb facs="tcp:9743:3"/>too tedious to vſe many wordes, where good wil is the bond of loue. This ſmal gift I would intreate you to accept, if not for the quantitie, yet for the qualitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From London <date>the thirteenth of October, 1610.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to commannd, <hi>SIL. IOVRDAN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF THE BARMV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAS, OTHER VVISE called the Ile of Diuels.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Being in ſhip called the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, with <hi>Sir THOMAS Gates,</hi> our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, <hi>Sir GEORGE Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptaine <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> three moſt worthy honoured Gentlemen, (whoſe valour and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude the world muſt needes take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice off, and that in moſt Honourable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9743:4"/>deſignes) bound for Virginia, in the height of thirty degrees of northerly latitude, or thereabouts: we were taken with a moſt ſharpe and cruell ſtorme vpon the fiue and twentieth day of Iuly, <hi>Anno 1609.</hi> which did not only ſeparate vs from the reſidue of our fleete, (which were eight in number) but with the violent wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Seas, our ſhip became ſo ſhaken, torne, and leaked, that ſhee receiued ſo much water, as couered two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire of hogſheads aboue the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt; that our men ſtoode vp to the middles, with buckets, baricos, and kettles, to baile out the water, and continually pumped for three dayes and three nights together, without any intermiſſion; and yet the water ſeemed rather to increaſe, then to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh: in ſo much that all our men, being vtterly ſpent, tyred, and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for longer labour, were euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, without any hope of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9743:4"/>liues, to ſhut vp the hatches, and to haue committed themſelues to the mercy of the ſea, (which is ſaid to be mercileſſe) or rather to the mercy of their mighty God and redeemer, (whoſe mercies exceed all his works) ſeeing no helpe, nor hope, in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of mans reaſon, that any mothers child could eſcape that ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable danger, which euery man had propoſed and digeſted to himſelfe, of preſent ſinking. So that ſome of them hauing ſome good and comfortable waters in the ſhip, fetcht them, and drunke one to the other, taking their laſt leaue one of the other, vntill their more ioyfull and happy meeting, in a more bleſſed world; when it pleaſed God out of his moſt gracious and mercifull prouidence, ſo to direct and guide our ſhip, (being left to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the ſea) for her moſt aduantage; that <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> (ſitting vpon the poope of the ſhip, (where he ſate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9743:5"/>three dayes and three nights toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without meales meate, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no ſleepe) couning the ſhippe to keepe her as vpright as he could, (for otherwiſe ſhee muſt needes inſtantly haue foundred) moſt wiſhedly happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcryed land; whereupon he moſt comfortably encouraged the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to follow their pumping, and by no meanes to ceaſe bayling out of the water, with their buckets, baricos, and kettles; whereby they were ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wearied, and their ſpirits ſo ſpent with long faſting, and continuance of their labour, that for the moſt part they were fallen aſleepe in corners, and whereſoeuer they chanced firſt to ſit or lie: but hearing news of land, wherewith they grew to bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what reuiued, being carried with wil and deſire beyond their ſtrength, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man buſled vp, and gathered his ſtrength and feeble ſpirits together, to performe as much as their weake
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9743:5"/>force would permit him: through which weake meanes, it pleaſed God to worke ſo ſtrongly as the water was ſtaide for that little time, (which as we all much feared, was the laſt period of our breathing) and the ſhip kept from preſent ſinking, when it pleaſed God to ſend her within halfe an Engliſh mile, of that land that <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> had not long before diſcryed: Which were the Ilandes of the Barmudas. And there neither did our ſhip ſincke, but more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in ſo great a misfortune, fell in betweene two rockes, where ſhee was faſt lodged and locked, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther budging: whereby we gayned, not only ſufficient time, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helpe of our boate, and skiffe, ſafely to ſet, and conuey our men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore (which were one hundred and fifty in number) but afterwards had time and leaſure to ſaue ſome good part of our goodes and prouiſion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9743:6"/>which the water had not ſpoyled, with all the tackling of the ſhip, and much of the yron about her, which were neceſſaries not a litle auaileable, for the building and furniſhing of a new ſhip and pinnis, which we made there, for the tranſporting and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vs to Virginia. But our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery was not more ſtrange in falling ſo opportunely, and happily vpon the land, as our feeding and preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was beyond our hopes, and all mens expectations moſt admirable. For the Ilands of the Barmudas, as euery man knoweth that hath heard or read of them, were neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by any Chriſtian or Heathen people, but euer eſteemed, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a moſt prodigious and inchanted place, affoording nothing but guſts, ſtormes, and foule weather; which made euery Nauigator and Mariner to auoide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Scylla and Charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis; or as they would ſhunne the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9743:6"/>himſelfe; and no man was euer heard, to make for the place, but as againſt their wils, they haue by ſtormes and dangerouſneſſe of the rocks, lying ſeauen leagues into the Sea, ſuffered ſhipwracke; yet did we finde there the ayre ſo temperate and the Country ſo aboundantly fruitful of all fit neceſſaries, for the ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and preſeruation of mans life, that moſt in a manner of all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions of bread, beare, and victuall, being quite ſpoyled, in lying long drowned in ſalt water, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we were there for the ſpace of nine moneths (few dayes ouer or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) not only well refreſhed, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and with good ſatiety contented, but out of the aboundance thereof, prouided vs ſome reaſonable quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and proportion of prouiſion, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vs for Virginia, and to maintaine our ſelues, and that company wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound there, to the great releefe of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9743:7"/>them, as it fell out in their ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and in reſpect of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, vntill it pleaſed God, that by my Lords comming thither, their ſtore was better ſupplyed. And greater, and better prouiſions wee might haue made, if we had had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes for the ſtoring and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation thereof. Wherefore my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſincerely of this Iland is, that whereas it hath beene, and is ſtill accounted, the moſt dangerous infortunate, and moſt forlorne place of the world, it is in truth the richeſt, healthfulleſt, and pleaſing land, (the quantity and bigneſſe thereof conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) and meerely naturall, as euer man ſet foote vpon: the particular profits and benefits whereof, ſhal be more eſpecially inſerted, and hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed, which euery man to his owne priuate knowledge, that was there, can auouch and iuſtifie for a truth. Vpon the eight and twentieth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9743:7"/>day of Iuly <hi>1609.</hi> (after the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the ſtorme, was ſomething qualified) we fell vpon the ſhore at the Barmudas; where after our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Sir Thomas Gates, Sir George Sommers,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Newport,</hi> had by their prouident carefulneſſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all their men, and ſo much of the goods and prouiſions out of the ſhip, as was not vtterly ſpoyled, euerie man diſpoſed and applyed himſelfe, to ſearch for, and to ſeeke out ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and ſuſtentation, as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try afforded: and <hi>Sir George Sommers,</hi> a man inured to extremities, (and knowing what thereunto belonged) was in this ſeruice, neither idle nor backward, but preſently by his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full induſtry, went and found out ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, of many kind of fiſhes, and ſo plentifull thereof, that in halfe an houre, he tooke ſo many great fiſhes with hookes, as did ſuffice the whole company one day. And fiſh is there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9743:8"/>ſo aboundant, that if a man ſteppe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water, they will come round about him; ſo that men were faine to get out for feare of byting. Theſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes are very fat and ſweete, and of that proportion and bigneſſe, that three of them will conueniently lade two men: thoſe we called rock fiſh. Beſides there are ſuch aboundance of mullets, that with a ſeane might be taken at one draught one thouſand at the leaſt, and infinite ſtore of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, with diuers kindes of great fiſhes, the names of them vnknowne to me: of crayfiſhes very great ones, and ſo great ſtore as that there hath beene taken in one night with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lights, euen ſufficient to feede the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany a day. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try affordeth great aboundance of Hogs, as that there hath beene taken by <hi>Sir George Sommers,</hi> who was the firſt that hunted for them, to the number of two and thirty at one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9743:8"/>time, which he brought to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in a boate, built by his owne hads. There is Fowle in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Ilands, where they breed, that there hath beene taken in two or three houres, a thouſand at the leaſt; the bird being of the bigneſſe of a good Pidgeon, and layeth egges as bigge as Hen egges vpon the ſand, where they come and lay them day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although men ſit downe amongſt them; that there hath beene taken vp in one morning, by <hi>Sir Thomas Gates</hi> men, one thouſand of egges: and <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> men, comming a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſtance of time after them, haue ſtayed there whilſt they came and layed their eggs amongſt them, that they brought away as many more with them; with many young birds very fat and ſweet. Another Sea fowle there is that lyeth in litle holes in the ground, like vnto a cony-hole, and are in great numbers, exceeding
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9743:9"/>good meate, very fat and ſweet (thoſe we had in the winter) and their eggs are white, and of that bigneſſe, that they are not to be knowne from Hen egges. The other birds egges are ſpeckled, and of a different colour: there are alſo great ſcore and plenty of Herons, and thoſe ſo familiar and tame, that wee beate them downe from the trees with ſtones and ſtaues; but ſuch were young Herons: beſides many white Herons, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as a blacke or gray fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on them; with other ſmall birds ſo tame and gentle, that a man wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the woods with a ſlicke, and whiſtling to them, they wil come and gaze on you, ſo neare that you may ſtrike and kill many of them with your ſticke; and with ſinging and hollowing you may doe the like. There are alſo great ſtore of Torto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (which ſome call Turtles) and thoſe ſo great, that I haue ſeene a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9743:9"/>buſhel of egges in one of their bellies, which are ſweeter then any Henne egge: and the Tortoſe it ſelfe, is all very good meate, and yeeldeth great ſtore of oyle, which is as ſweete as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny butter; and one of them will ſuffice fifty men a meale, at the leaſt: and of theſe hath beene taken great ſtore, with two boates, at the leaſt forty in one day. The Country yeeldeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers fruits, as prickled peares, great aboundance, which continue greene vpon the trees all the yeare; alſo great plenty of Mulberries, white and red: and on the ſame are great ſtore of Silke-wormes, which yeeld cods of ſilke, both white and yellow, being ſome courſe, and ſome fine. And there is a tree called a Palmito tree, which hath a very ſweet berry, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the hogs doe moſt feede; but our men finding the ſweetneſſe of them, did willingly ſhare with the hogs for them, they being very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9743:10"/>and wholſome, which made them careleſſe almoſt of any bread with their meate; which occaſioned vs to carry in a manner all that ſtore of flower and meale, we did or could ſaue for Virginia. The head of the Palmito tree is very good meate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raw or ſodden, it yeeldeth a head which waigheth about twenty pound, and is farre better meate, then any cabbidge. There are an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Cedar trees, (the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt I thinke in the world) and thoſe bring forth a very ſweet berry, and wholſome to eate. The Country (for as much as I could find my ſelf, or heare by others) affords no veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous creature, or ſo much as a Rat or Mouſe, or any other thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſome. There is great ſtore of Pearle, and ſome of them very faire, round, and Orientall; and you ſhall finde at leaſt one hundred ſeede of Pearle in one Oyſter; there hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9743:10"/>beene likewiſe found, ſome good quantity of Amber Greece, and that of the beſt ſort. There are alſo great plenty of Whales, which I conceaue are very eaſie to be killed, for they come ſo vſually, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to the ſhore, that we heard them oftentimes in the night a bed; and haue ſeene many of them neare the ſhore, in the day time. There was borne vpon the Barmudas, at the time of our being there two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the one a man child, there bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, by the name of Barmudas: and a woman child, baptiſed by the name of Barmuda: as alſo there was a marriage betweene two En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh people vpon that Iland. This Iland, I meane the mayne Iland, with all the broken Ilandes adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, are made in the forme of a half Moone, but a little more rounder, and diuided into many broken I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9743:11"/>and there are many good harbours in it, but wee could finde one eſpeciall place to goe in, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to goe out from it, which was not altogether free from ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and that lyeth on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt-ſide, where there is three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoms water, at the entrance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but within ſixe, ſeauen, or eight fathoms at the leaſt, where you may ſafely lie land-locked, from the danger of all winds and weathers, and more to the trees. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into it, is ſo narrow and ſtraight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the rocks, as that it will with ſmall ſtore of munition be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and eaſily defended, with all aduantage the place affords, againſt the forces of the Potenteſt King of Europe. There are alſo plenty of Haukes, and very good Tobacco, as I thinke, which through forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, I had almoſt omitted:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9743:11"/>now hauing finiſhed and rigged our ſhip, and pinnis, the one called the Deliuerance, the pinnis the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, wee prepared and made our ſelues ready, to ſhip for Virginia, hauing powdred ſome ſtore of hogs fleſh, for prouiſion thither, and the company thereof, for ſome reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time: but were compelled to make ſalt there for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for all our ſalt was ſpent and ſpoyled, before wee recouered the ſhore. Wee carryed with vs alſo a good portion of Tortoſe oyle, which either for frying or baking did vs very great pleaſure, it being very ſweete, nouriſhing, and wholſome: the greateſt defects we found there, was tarre and pitch for our ſhip and pinnis, in ſteede whereof wee were forced to make lime there of a hard kinde of ſtone, and vſe it: which for the preſent occaſion and neceſſity,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9743:12"/>with ſome wax we found caſt vp by the Sea, from ſome ſhip wracke, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the turne to pay the ſeames of the pinnis <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> built, for which hee had neither pitch nor tarre: ſo that God in the ſupplying of all our wants, beyond all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhewed himſelfe ſtill mercifull vnto vs, that we might accompliſh our intended voyage to Virginia, for which I confidently hope, hee doth yet reſerue a bleſſing in ſtore, and to the which I preſume, euery honeſt and religious heart will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily giue their Amen. When all thinges were made ready, and commodiouſly fitted, the winde comming faire, wee ſet ſaile and put off from the Barmudas, the tenth day of May, in the yeare <hi>1610.</hi> and arriued at Iames towne in Virginia, the foure and twentieth day of the ſame Moneth: where
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9743:12"/>wee found ſome threeſcore perſons liuing. And being then ſome three weeks or thereabouts paſſed, &amp; not hearing of anye ſupply, it was thought fitting by a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to vſe the beſt meanes for the preſeruation of all thoſe people that were liuing, being all in number two hundred perſons. And ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eight of Iune one thouſand ſix hundred and ten, wee imbarked at Iames Towne: not hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fourteene dayes victaile, and ſo were determined to direct our courſe for new-found-land, there to refreſh vs, and ſupply our ſelues with victaile, to bring vs home; but it pleaſed God to diſpoſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of vs, and to giue vs better meanes. For being all of vs ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in foure pinnices, and departed from the towne, almoſt downe half the Riuer, wee met my Lord de la
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9743:13"/>Warre comming vp with three ſhips, well furniſhed with victaile, which reuiued all the company, and gaue them great content. And after ſome few dayes, my Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the great plenty of Hogges and Fiſh, was at the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas, and the neceſſity of them in Virginia, was deſirous to ſend thither, to ſupply himſelfe with thoſe things, for the better com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting of his men, and the planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Country. Whereupon <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> being a man beſt acquainted with the place, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to doe ſeruice vnto his Prince and Country: without any reſpect of his owne priuate gaine: and being of threeſcore yeares of age at the leaſt, out of his worthy and valiant minde, offered himſelfe to vndertake to performe with Gods help that dangerous voyage
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9743:13"/>for the Barmudas, for the better releefe and comfort of the people in Virginia, and for the better planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, which offer my Lord de la warre, very willingly and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accepted: and ſo vpon the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of Iune, <hi>Sir George Sommers</hi> imbarked himſelf at Iames towne in a ſmall barge of thirty tonne, or therabout, that he built at the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas: wherein he laboured from morning vntill night, as duelie as any workeman doth labour for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and built her all with Cedar, with little or no yron worke at all: hauing in her but one boult, which was in the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon: notwithſtanding thanks be to God, ſhee brought vs in ſafety to Virginia, and ſo I truſt he will protect him, and ſend him well backe againe, to his hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and the great comfort of all the company there.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9743:14"/>
            <p>The Barmudas lyeth in the height of two and thirty degrees and a halfe, of Northerly latitude, Virginia bearing directly from it, Weſt, North weſt, two hundred and thirty leagues.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9743:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
